<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string-array name="storyContents">
        <item>Discover Red Fort in Delhi which is one of the famous places in India. Meet the boss of Indian historical places. If you consider the top 10 historical places in India, Taj Mahal will always be ranking high in the list. Explore the ultimate epitome of love, the Taj Mahal, whose grandeur remains unmatched in history and today this is one of the weekend getaways from Delhi. This opulent white marble structure was commissioned to be built in 1632 by Shah Jahan for his late wife Mumtaz Mahal. It took around 22 years to complete this magnificent structure that is considered one of the most famous historical places in India.
According to local legend, it was believed that Shah Jahan cut off the hands of all the workers who built the Taj Mahal so that a similar monument could not be built.
\n\nInteresting fact: A shopping complex and hotel inspired by the Taj Mahal is being constructed in Dubai and is estimated to be four times larger in size.
\n\nBuilt By: Shah Jahan
\n\nBuilt In: 1648
</item>
        <item>To get a sense of the rich history of the Mughal era, visit the walled palatial Agra Fort, one of the famous historical places in India that is built entirely of red sandstone. Built in 1565 by Akbar, this historical tourist place in India has two ornately designed gates: the Amar Singh Gate and the Delhi Gate. You can only enter through the Amar Singh Gate to uncover an ancient city filled with gateways, courts, passages, palaces and mosques. It is one of the most beautiful places to visit in Agra.
\n\nInteresting fact: This fort was included in one of Sherlock Holmes’ cases: the “Sign of the Four” and was also the location for the movie Jodha Akbar.
\n\nPlaces:Jahangir Palace, Nagina Masjid, Moti Masjid, Mina Masjid and Zenana Mina Bazaar.
\n\nBuilt By: Akbar and Shah Jahan
\n\nBuilt In: 1573
</item>
        <item>One of the historical tourist places in India, the Red Fort was constructed over ten years from 1638 to 1648. This fort was constructed when Shah Jahan shifted the capital from Agra to Delhi and it was then known as the Qila-e-Mubarak. This octagonal fort is one of the most famous historical places in north India and is also the site where the President gives his speech on Independence Day. The Red fort is truly remarkable and one of the best historical places in India.
\n\nInteresting fact: The Red fort was actually white as it was made of limestone. The British painted it red when the limestone started chipping off.
\n\nPlaces: The Palace of Colors or the ‘Rang Mahal’ where the emperor’s wives, mistresses and maids resided.
\n\nBuilt By: Shah Jahan
\n\nBuilt In: 1639
</item>
        <item>Regarded as the site of the first Muslim kingdom in northern India, the Qutub Minar is definitely one of the most historical sites in India. It is one of the finest examples of Indo-Muslim architecture with its intricate red sandstone storeys. These are dotted with carvings and verses from the Quran and are mostly in Arabic and Nagari. Qutub Minar is one of the famous historical places in India and is said to have got its name from Qutb-ud-din Aibak who was the first Muslim ruler of North India. The first mosque in India Quwwat-ul-Islam Masjid is also located at the foot of the Qutub Minar.
\n\nInteresting fact: The Qutub Minar complex has an iron pillar that has not rusted even after 2000 years.
\n\nPlaces: The Decorative Light Show held every evening from 6:30 to 8 pm and the Qutub Minar Festival that is held in October/November.
\n\nBuilt By: Qitub-ud-Din Aibak
\n\nBuilt In: 1193</item>
        <item>A beautiful synthesis of Indian and Persian architecture, Humayun’s Tomb is one of the most famous and important places in India. Humayun’s wife Hamida Banu Begum commissioned the building of this tomb for her husband in the 15th century. Arched alcoves, beautiful domes, elaborate corridors and kiosks – all make this monument a grandeur of Indian architecture. There is also a barber’s tomb at the southwestern side of the main tomb. It is one of the most famous tourist places in Delhi that one should certainly visit.
\n\nInteresting fact: Humayun’s Tomb was one of the main inspirations for the Taj Mahal.
\n\nPlaces:‘The Dormitory of the Mughals’ that has over 100 tombs of the Mughal emperors.
\n\nBuilt By: Mirak Mirza Ghiyath
\n\nBuilt In: 1572
</item>
        <item>The royal city of Fatehpur Sikri was once the capital of the Mughal era during Akbar’s reign. This royal city is one of the historical tourist places in India and once had palaces, public buildings, mosques, quarters for the king, the army as well as the servants. Further, the well planned royal city with carved columns and decorated pillars was built between 1571-1573 AD and abandoned due to a shortage of water.
\n\nInteresting fact: Many barren women would come to the tomb of the Sufi saint Salim Chisti to pray for children.
\n\nPlaces: Diwan-i-Aam and the Diwan-i-Khas
\n\nBuilt By: Akbar
\n\nBuilt In: 1569
</item>
        <item>Image Source
The ‘Palace of Winds’ or Hawa Mahal gets its name due to the fact that it looks like a honeycomb of a beehive with its 953 intricate windows. It is also shaped like a crown as the ruler who built it, Maharaja Sawai Pratap Singh, was a major devotee of Lord Krishna. One of the popular tourist places in Jaipur, this palace is known as the tallest building in the world that doesn’t have any foundation. The palace is curved but still stands firm due to its pyramidal shape.
\n\nInteresting fact: It was believed that this building was created so that the royal ladies could look outside as they were constantly under ‘purdah’
\n\nPlaces: The intricate lattice work on the tiny windows.
\n\nBuilt By: Pratap Singh
\n\nBuilt In: 1799
</item>
        <item>Khajuraho has always been thought of as the place that exemplifies sensuality and eroticism at its best. However this is a misrepresentation as only about 10 percent of the sculptures are sensual and the rest are common depictions. Countless sculptures depicting love, eternal grace, beauty, delicacy and the creative arts can be seen in one of the most historical places in India. A perfect amalgamation of Hinduism and Jainism, Khajuraho temples have carvings of cult icons, demi gods and Apsaras.
\n\nInteresting fact: The city got its name as it was adorned with date palms and “Khajura’ means date palms in Hindi. It was also often called Khajjurpura in ancient times.
\n\nPlaces: The Sound and Light Show that portrays the tale of the Chandela dynasty.
\n\nBuilt By: Chandela dynasty
\n\nBuilt In: Between 950 AD and 1050 AD
</item>
        <item>Unearth one of the most religious centers of Buddhism at the Sanchi Stupa that houses relics of the Buddha. This famous historical place in India was built by Lord Asoka in the 3rd century B.C for Emperor Ashoka. The Dome of the Stupa signifies the wheel of law and this stupa is actually considered as a symbol of Buddha’s freedom the circle of life and death (Moksha). The four gateways of the Stupa have various scenes from the Jataka tales and stories of Buddha’s life.
\n\nInteresting fact: The relics of Buddha were painted with a Mauryan polish to make them glow like glass.
\n\nPlaces: The Ashoka pillar has four lions and is designed in a Greco-Buddhist style. It is also the national emblem of India.
\n\nBuilt By: Emperor Ashoka
\n\nBuilt In: 3rd century BCE
</item>
        <item>Built by the great ruler of the Ganga dynasty – King Narasimhadeva I, along with 1200 artisans, the Konark Temple is magic set in stone. Located on the coast of the Bay of Bengal, this temple signifies the exquisite detailing of ancient architecture and is one of the famous historical places in India. A particularly interesting feat is at the entrance of the temple where two lions are shown crushing elephants and a human body lies at the foot of the elephant.
\n\nInteresting fact: The 12 wheels at the base of the temple are sundials that accurately denote time.
\n\nPlaces: The three statues of the sun gods where the sun’s rays fall at dawn, noon and sunset.
\n\nBuilt By: Raja Narasinghs Deva I
\n\nBuilt In: 13th century BCE
</item>
        <item>Visit the Mahabodhi temples that are one of the four holy grounds of Buddhism. This is the spot where the Buddha is said to have attained enlightenment while meditating under a fig tree. The Bodhi tree is the descendant of the Fig tree and lies just near the temple. The earliest temple was built by Ashoka in the 3rd century BC. The temple has a massive statue of Buddha touching the earth with this right hand.
\n\nInteresting fact: The Bodhimanda is the spot under the Bodhi tree where the Buddha attained enlightenment. It is believed that this spot will be the last to disappear when the world ends and the first to reappear when the world is recreated.
\n\nPlaces: The Jewel Walk here is the spot where the Buddha is said to have gone on a seven days walking meditation after he was enlightened.
\n\nBuilt By: Emperor Ashoka
\n\nBuilt In: 3rd century BCE
</item>
        <item>You will feel like an ant climbing down an anthill when you explore the Rani ki Vav stepwell as it is a massive structure that is around 24 meters deep. One of the most unexplored historical places in India, this stepwell was built in the 11th century AD, as a memoriam for King Bhimdev of the Solanki dynasty by his wife Queen Udayamati. The lowest level of the stepwell was earlier used as a route to escape to neighbouring villages. It is one of the most beautiful places to visit in Gujarat.
\n\nInteresting fact: The central level has the theme “Dasavatars” which means 10 incarnations of Vishnu, and that when you approach the water level there will be a sculpture of Vishnu reclining on a thousand snake heads.
\n\nPlaces: The excellently carved sculptures of Yokinis, Apsaras and Nakakanyas in the seven galleries.
\n\nBuilt By: Udayamati
\n\nBuilt In: 11th century AD
</item>
        <item>The Victoria Memorial in Kolkata is one of the most historical tourist places in India and was built during the peak of the British era in India. The then Viceroy Lord Curzon laid down the idea of this monument but its actual design was done by Sir William Emerson.
Multitudes of lush gardens, a museum filled with British memorabilia including weapons, paintings, sculptures, artifacts etc and royal portrait of the Queen are what you will find in this beautiful monument. One of the best paintings you will find here is the one by Russian artist Vasili Verestchagin. This painting depicts the Prince of Wales in Jaipur in 1876.
\n\nInteresting fact: There are two sets of mysterious inscriptions on the monument. One is “VRI” which means Victoria Regina Imperatrix and the other is “Dieu Et Mon Droit”. The first means Victoria Queen and Empress and the latter means “God and my right”.
\n\nPlaces: The black bronze statue “Angel of Victory” that lies on the apex of the memorial’s dome. In favorable weather, it also acts as a weathercock.
\n\nBuilt By: Lord Curzon
\n\nBuilt In: 1921
</item>
        <item>The infamous Jallianwala Bagh massacre took place near this monument near the Golden Temple in Amritsar. Covering around 6.5 acres, it is the place where General Dyer ordered a mass shooting on Baisakhi. Thousands of innocents succumbed to death in this incident. It was one of the incidents that ignited the fire of Independence revolution. A memorial was erected here on 13th April 1961 by the then president, Dr. Rajendra Prasad.
\n\nInteresting fact: Infamous Jallianwala Bagh Massacre took place here
\n\nPlaces: The step well that took the centre stage during the massacre.
\n\nBuilt By: Benjamin Polk (memorial)
\n\nBuilt In: 1961 (memorial)
</item>
        <item>A legendary fort of its time, Gwalior Fort has been around for a long time. Some sources suggest that it was constructed in or before 6 century Mughal Emporer Babur described this place to be a pearl among Indian fortresses. The second oldest reference to the number zero can be found here. Situated in the historic city of Gwalior, it is the part of the identity of the city that has seen many dynasties come and go.
\n\nInteresting fact: Second oldest reference to number zero is carved here, it was constructed in the 6th century.
\n\nPlaces: Man Mandir, Gujari Palace, Jahangir Palace, and the Karan Palace
\n\nBuilt By: Man Singh Tomar
\n\nBuilt In: 3rd century BCE (later developed into the fort it is today)
</item>
        <item>One of the most famous Gurudwara in the entire world, Sri Harmandir Sahib is one of the important spiritual places in India. While it has been around for a long while, it was rebuilt with pure gold and marble in 1830 by Maharaja Ranjit Singh. Located in the heart of Amritsar, it is visited by more than a hundred thousand pilgrims every day.

\n\nInteresting fact: Each day, over a hundred thousand people partake the Langar here
\n\nPlaces: Amrit Sarovar, Ramgarhia Bunga
\n\nBuilt By: Guru Ram Das
\n\nBuilt In: 1599
</item>
        <item>This 42-meter monument is often compared with Arch de Triomphe in Paris and Arch of Constantine in Rome. Located on the Rajpath, it was designed by Edwin Lutyens. Dedicated to the 82,000 soldiers of both Indian and British descent who fought in World War One and 13,300 soldiers who were martyred in the 3rd Anglo-Afghan War, it was built in 1931. Every year, the Republic Day Parade is held here. It is a famous destination among both locals and tourists.
\n\nInteresting fact: Dedicated to nearly 1 lakh soldiers who perished in two wars, namely WW I and Third Anglo-Afghan War. It is the spot where Amar Jawan Jyoti – the eternal flame- continues to burn.
\n\nPlaces: Amar Jawan Jyoti, Children’s Park
\n\nBuilt By: Edwin Lutyens
\n\nBuilt In: 1921
</item>
        <item>Commissioned by Rao Jodha in 1459, it is one of the biggest forts in India. There are 7 entrances in the complex which is nestled on a hill. Each gate was constructed at different times for different purposes. For example, the Vijay Gate was built to mark the win of King Man Singh over Bikaner and Jaipur. There is a Rose palace and a Glass Palace within the complex. This fort has been featured in a number of Bollywood and Hollywood movies as well.
\n\nInteresting fact: It is situated at an elevation of 410 m
\n\nPlaces: The seven gates and the smaller palace complexes.
\n\nBuilt By: Rao Jodha
\n\nBuilt In: 1459
</item>
        <item>Only 11 km from the Pink City Jaipur, Amer Fort is one of the most magnificent forts in India. Built by Maharaja Man Singh in 1592, it was truly the residence of kings. Another UNESCO site in the heart of Rajasthan. Made of yellow and pink sandstone, it is an unforgettable sight. Over 5 thousand people visit this fort every day, making it one of the most visited places in Jaipur.
\n\nInteresting fact: King Man Singh I was one of the most decorated generals of King Akbar
\n\nPlaces: Elephant Ride, The Interiors
\n\nBuilt By: Raja Man Singh I
\n\nBuilt In: 1592
</item>
        <item>Another famous fort in Rajasthan, it is famous for the majestic fort as well as the wildlife sanctuary. Built by King Kumbha, it falls under the care of the district of Rajasamand. It is also only 82 km from Udaipur, making it a great day trip if you are in the city. It is a major tourist attraction due to the magnificent structure of the palace.
\n\nInteresting fact: The walls of Kumbhalgarh are the second longest in the world after the Great Wall of China
\n\nPlaces: Kumbha Mahal, Badal Mahal, Hanuman Pol, Neelkanth Mahadev Temple
\n\nBuilt By: Rana Kumbha
\n\nBuilt In: 1458
</item>
        <item>Built by the prestigious Gaekwad family who ruled Baroda. Initially a part of Sarkar Wada, it was built in 1890 by Maharaja Sayajirao Gaekwad. The palace is one of a kind with Indo-Saracenic architecture. The interiors are European-inspired and the grounds have a gold course that was used to entertain British guests. It remains one of the unknown historical places in India.
\n\nInteresting fact: the Lakshmi Vilas is four times the size of Buckingham Palace, and is said to be largest private residence to be built at that time.
\n\nPlaces: Royal Armoury, Gaddi Hall, Coronation Room
\n\nBuilt By: Maharaja Sayajirao Gaekwad III
\n\nBuilt In: 1890
</item>
        <item>Built as an access point for the entry and exit during the British period, the Gateway of India is one of the important places in India. This ancient gateway was completed in 1924 and was inaugurated by The Viceroy, the Earl of Reading. It has been reinforced over time using yellow basalt and concrete and has delicate lattice work all over the turrets. The statues of Chhatrapati Shivaji and Swami Vivekananda were also installed at the Gateway later on.
\n\nInteresting fact: The last of the British ships set sail for England from the Gateway of India in the 20th century.
\n\nPlaces: There are steps behind the gateway from where you can take trips to Elephanta Island.
\n\nBuilt By: George Wittet
\n\nBuilt In: 1913</item>
        <item>The Ajanta-Ellora caves depict true craftsmanship skills where each rock carving was done by hand. When British officer John Smith set out to chase a tiger in 1819, he would never have thought that he would uncover the majestic Ajanta caves. These 29 caves are full of sculptures and paintings that epitomize Buddha and various Jataka tales.
Blending three different religions: Buddhism, Jainism and Brahmanism, the 34 caves at Ellora have been carved on the walls of a basaltic hill. There are 12 Buddhist caves, 17 Hindu caves and 5 Jain caves. Most of these caves are monasteries that were used for praying and studying.
\n\nInteresting fact: It is believed that the Buddhist monks were not allowed to go out during the monsoons and would sit and carve sculptures in the Ajanta caves.
\n\nAjanta: Cave 26 which is an elaborately decorated Chaitya hall with a stupa.
\n\nEllora: The ‘Cavern of the Ten Avatars’ built under the reign of Krishna I.
\n\nBuilt By: Satavahanas, Vakataka
\n\nBuilt In: 200 BC to 100 AD, 5th century AD
</item>
        <item>It was believed that Muhammad Quli Qutb Shah built the Charminar in 1591 to honor Allah. However in reality this historical tourist place in India was built to signify the end of plague in the city. Legend has it that there is a secret tunnel from the monument to Golconda fort but it hasn’t been discovered till date. Each minaret of this monument has four stories and every arch has one clock.
\n\nInteresting fact: There is a cat’s head in one of the arches in order to ward off rats that once almost destroyed Hyderabad.
\n\nPlaces: Laad Bazaar is an ideal spot to pick up a number of unique artifacts and there are several food joints in the market itself.
\n\nBuilt By: Muhammad Quli Qutb Shah
\n\nBuilt In: 1591
</item>
        <item>Once the royal abode of a number of rulers, the Mysore Palace is now a museum that has all the royal pictures, clothing and artifacts of the Wodeyar dynasty. This palace is one of the most historical places in India and is frequently visited by several tourists. The palace was built and refined by several emperors throughout the years and is thus an amalgamation of Hindu, Rajput, and Mughal styles making it one of the heritage destinations in India. Glazed tiles, chandeliers, and iron pillars adorn the pavilion inside the temple that is used to host royal weddings.
\n\nInteresting fact: The Maharajas used to earlier sit on a Golden palanquin that was then carried by elephants during the Dasara festival. Goddess Durga’s idol is now placed inside the palanquin.
\n\nPlaces: The way the palace is lighted up during the Dussehra festival with over 10,000 lights.
\n\nBuilt By: Maharaja Krishnaraja Wadiyar IV
\n\nBuilt In: 1897
</item>
        <item>Hampi’s rocky outcrops, chariot structures, gopurams, elephant stables, ornate halls – all depict the tale of one of the greatest Hindu kingdoms. It is believed that Lord Rama and his brother visited this historical place to search for Sita. They took the help of the two brothers Bali and Sugriv who ruled this region then. This UNESCO World Heritage Site is one of the most famous historical places in South India and was also the region where Vijayanagara’s main coin mint was situated.
\n\nInteresting fact: The first instance of human settlement recorded here dates all the way back to 1 CE.
\n\nPlaces: Hampi Monuments that have carvings from the 14th century.
\n\nBuilt By: Lakkana Dandesha
\n\nBuilt In: 1570
</item>
        <item>Get set to undertake an adventurous journey back in time by visiting the trio of three great Chola temples: Brihadeshwara Temple at Tanjore, Airavateshwara Temple in Darasuram, and Brihadeeshwara Temple in Gangaikonda Cholapuram. The three temples were built by the kings of Chola dynasty which was one of the greatest kingdoms of South India. The ones at Tanjore and Cholapuram were built in the 11th century while the one at Darasuram was built in the 12th century.
\n\nInteresting fact: Raja Raja Cholan was inspired to build the Brihadeshwara Temple at Tanjore due to a dream he had while visiting Sri Lanka.
\n\nPlaces: The first royal portrait at Brihadeshwara Temple where Raja Raja Cholan can be seen paying obeisance to Lord Natarajar.
\n\nBuilt By: Emperor Rajaraja
\n\nBuilt In: 1010
</item>
        <item>Dravidian-style temples dotted with innumerable sculptures are the major attractions of Mahabalipuram. The stone carvings display Pallava art and took over 200 years to create making this one of the most ancient historical places in India.
11 temples called Mandapas lie on both sides of the hills at Mahabalipuram and these have both Dravidian style architecture as well as several Buddhist elements. The Shore Temple, Arjuna’s Penance and the Cave temples are some of the most popular tourist attractions of this region.
\n\nInteresting fact: The “Descent of the Ganges” that has been carved from pink granite and displays how Lord Shiva made the water of the Ganges descend from the heavens onto the earth.
\n\nPlaces: Dance festivals are major tourist attractions of these Mahabalipuram temples. There is a Mamallapuram Dance Festival every year celebrated in the month of December or January.
</item>
        <item>A UNESCO world heritage site, it features a Victorian-Gothic style of architecture. It is a railway station of Mumbai, the capital of Maharashtra. Constructed in 1887, it is the headquarter of central railways. An iconic landmark of the financial hub of India, it looks timeless when compared with the rest of Mumbai. It is the place from where various long distance and short distance trains begin.
\n\nInteresting fact: It was built to commemorate the 50th birthday of Queen Victoria and took 10 years to be completed
\n\nPlaces: You must take a train ride from CST to get the essence of Bombay.
\n\nBuilt By: Frederick William Stevens
\n\nBuilt In: 1888
</item>
        <item>Created in 1656, Gol Gumbaz is the mausoleum of the seventh ruler of Adil Shah Dynasty, Mohammed Adil Shah. Gol Gumbaz literally means “circular dome”and is maintained by ASI (Archaeological Survey of India). It took 30 years to be built and is one of the most important places to visit in Kerala. It was designed by Yaqut of Dabul and also houses the wives and daughters of the Sultan of Bijapur.
\n\nInteresting fact: Made from Dark Grey Basalt with Deccan Indo-Islamic style of architecture and is known as Taj Mahal of South India
\n\nPlaces: Whispering Gallery, Crypt of the king and his family
\n\nBuilt By: Yaqut of Dabul
\n\nBuilt In:1656
</item>
        <item>Cellular Jail is one of the most popular attractions in Port Blair. The jail is stranded on a secluded island and was used by Britishers to punish miscreants. Cellular Jail means Kala Pani that translates to exile till death. Now the colonial prison has been turned into an attraction where people get a glimpse of prisoner’s life where they were treated in inhumane conditions. It is worth a visit if you are visiting Andaman - Nicobar Islands.
\n\nInteresting fact: Freedom fighters like Batukeshwar Dutt and Veer Sawarkar were imprisoned here during the time of Independence struggle.
\n\nPlaces: Light - Sound Show
\n\nBuilt By: British India
\n\nBuilt In: 1906
</item>
        <item>Elephanta Caves have been recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage Site. the cave depicts the rock-cut art and architecture from the medieval times in India. The caves date back to the 5th and 7th century. The caves are basically divided into two groups. The first group is the five Hindu Temples and the second group is of two Buddhist caves.
\n\nInteresting fact: The ferry ride to the caves from Mumbai is an interesting one
\n\nPlaces: Amazing view of the Mumbai skyline
\n\nBuilt By: Hinayana Buddhists
\n\nBuilt In: Between 5th to late 8th century AD
</item>
        <item>How can you not know about Jantar Mantar in Jaipur? It is the largest astronomical observatory in the world and one of the best historical places of India. The place was built by Raja Sawai Madho Singh in the 18th century as he was a big fan of science. There are instruments in the observatory placed in a such a way that it tells you the position of heavenly bodies.
\n\nInteresting fact: Jantar Mantar has the world’s largest sundial.
\n\nPlaces: Light - Sound Show
\n\nBuilt By: Maharaja Sawai Jai Singh II
\n\nBuilt In: 1735
</item>
        <item>Golkonda Fort is the icon of Hyderabad that was built to protect Hyderabad from the invasion of the foreign army. It is also the place where mighty Kohinoor diamond was placed. Everything about this fort, the grandiose architecture, its history and mystery, is alluring. You must definitely put this attraction on your itinerary when in Hyderabad.
\n\nInteresting fact: When you clap your hands at the bottom of the fort, it can be heard at the top.
\n\nPlaces: Light - Sound show
\n\nBuilt By: Sultan Quli Qutb-ul-Mulk
\n\nBuilt In: 1143
</item>
        <item>Located in the ‘City of Nawabs’, Bara Imambara is known for its architectural prowess and one of the top historical places of India. It is the world’s largest structure standing without the support of beams. It was constructed by Asif Imambara as an important place of worship for Muslims. You will even find an incredible maze of Bhool Bhulaiya inside the premises.
\n\nInteresting fact: There 1024 ways to get inside the maze, but only 2
\n\nPlaces: The grave of Nawab Asaf-Ud-Dowlah and his crown
\n\nBuilt By: Nawab Asaf-Ud-Daula
\n\nBuilt In: 1798
</item>
        <item>A historic hindu temple located on the southern bank of the Vaigai River in Madurai, this majestic temple is all about seeking good vibes, positivity and wholesome spirituality. It is dedicated to Parvati, known as Meenakshi, and her spouse, Shiva. Marvel at the magnificent architecture with intricate carvings and admire the great beauty of this temple. It is one of the most famous places in India.
\n\nInteresting Fact: The intricate architecture of the place is amongst the seven wonders of the world.
\n\nPlaces: The 14 gateways to the temple and the pillars.
\n\nBuilt By: King Kulasekara Pandya
\n\nBuilt In: 1216
</item>
        <item>Located in the Hassan district of Karnataka, it’s a collection of stunning temples with a glorious past, also known as the hidden gem of Indian architecture. If you are in search to visit some historical places in India, then Halebidu makes perfect sense. It has a magnificent temple complex representing a Hoysala architecture. It also houses a number of Jain temples and other significant structures ornament that will evoke in you a sense of spirituality.
\n\nInteresting Fact: It was the regal capital of the Hoysala Empire in the 12th century.
\n\nPlaces: The archaeological museum
\n\nBuilt By: King Vishnuvardhana
\n\nBuilt In: 1121
</item>
        <item>One of the largest forts and historical places of India, Chittorgarh, the capital of Mewar kingdom has a striking attraction known as the Chittorgarh Fort. This magnificent Fort stands tall and reflects the sheer beauty, and the glorious past of the Mewar rulers.  The fort is spread across 700 acres of land and is always remembered for its glorious battles, especially during the Alauddin khilji and self-sacrificing Jauhar performed by Rani Padmini.
\n\nInteresting Fact: It was the place where the famous self-sacrificing Jauhar was performed by Rani Padmini to thwart the conquest of the fort by Alauddin Khilji.
\n\nPlaces: Rani Padmini Palace
\n\nBuilt By: Chitrangad Mori
\n\nBuilt In: 7th century AD
</item>
        <item>The most popular Mahavihara of the ancient times, it’s a significant Buddhist seat of academic excellence and a modest pligrim centre. Seek spirituality, good vibes, positivity, calm and serenity at this one of the most enchanting Indian historical places.
\n\nInteresting Fact: The library of the university was so huge that during the attack by Muslims, it took more than 5 months for the library to burn down completely.
\n\nPlaces: Museum that houses a collection of bronzes, coins and artifacts.
\n\nBuilt By: Gupta Dynasty
\n\nBuilt In: 5th Century BC
</item>
        <item>Listed as part of the UNESCO World Heritage Site, this part of Goa marks the presence of the Portuguese that can be seen in the architecture of several convents and churches that were built in Goa as part of beginning of Christianity in India. The churches and convents of Goa are some of the most beautiful historical places of India.
\n\nInteresting Fact: Goa was the capital of Portuguese rule in India and this is part of their heritage.
\n\nPlaces: Basilica Of Bom Jesus
\n\nBuilt By: The Portuguese
\n\nBuilt In: 16th century
</item>
        <item>Orchha Fort Complex is a vast archaeological site that consists of several historical monuments – palaces and temple. It is located in Orchha Town of Madhya Pradesh and one of the best historical places in India. The palaces are Raja Mahal , Jahangir Mahal, and Sheesh Mahal. Apart from these, there is a temple and a garden, Phool Bagh located within the Orchha Fort.
\n\nInteresting Fact: A popular ancient temple in Orchha, the Ram Raja Temple is the only temple where Lord Ram is venerated as both a God and a king.
\n\nPlaces: Raja Mahal , Jahangir Mahal, and Sheesh Mahal
\n\nBuilt By: King Rudra Pratap Singh
\n\nBuilt In: 1501
</item>
        <item>Bhimbetka Rock Shelters in Madhya Pradesh are an archaeological site dating back to the prehistoric age and one of the famous places in India. They preserve evidences of Stone Age in form of ancient cave paintings. The paintings are believed to be about 30, 000 years old. In 2003, Bhimbetka was recognized as a UNESCO World Heritage Site. There are around 500 caves and rock shelters that helps it qualify for the best historical places in India.
\n\nInteresting Fact: Though the existence of Bhimbetka caves dates back to several years, they were discovered only in 1957.
\n\nPlaces: Cave paintings
\n\nBuilt By: Early Humans
\n\nBuilt In: Early Times
</item>
        <item>Sitting in Gujarat, Champaner Pavagadh Archaeological Park has found itself a place on the list of UNESCO World Sites. Sitting in the heart of Champaner and being surrounded by Pavagadh Hills, this Archaeological Park is one of the most beautiful historical places in India along with being of mythological significance. One can witness an extensive number of architectural marvels that both showcase the styles of Hindu and Islamic designs.
\n\nInteresting Fact: It is believed that the Pavagadh hill is a chunk of the Himalayas that was carried by Lord Hanuman to Lanka in the famous Hindu Epic – Ramayana.
\n\nPlaces: The Hindu and Islamic styles of architecture
\n\nBuilt By: Vanraj Chavda
\n\nBuilt In: 8th century AD
</item>


    </string-array>
</resources>